<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Dermatology on</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/tags/Dermatology/</link><description>Recent content in Dermatology on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://notes.nosos.co.uk/tags/Dermatology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Atopic dermatitis and eczema</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Atopic-dermatitis-eczema/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Atopic-dermatitis-eczema/</guid><description>Acute or chronic inflammation of the dermis. Often appears in childhood and can continue to adulthood.
Atopy - triad of dermatitis/eczema, asthma and allergic rhinitis (hay fever)</description></item><item><title>Basal Cell Carcinoma</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Basal-Cell-Carcinoma/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Basal-Cell-Carcinoma/</guid><description>aka rodent ulcer
![[z_attachments/Pasted image 20231110123945.png|300]] Nodular BCC
![[z_attachments/Pasted image 20231110124436.png|575]]
Causes/Factors The primary cause is prolonged exposure to ultraviolet (UV) radiation from the sun or tanning beds.</description></item><item><title>Cellulitis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Cellulitis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Cellulitis/</guid><description>Cellulitis is a common bacterial skin infection that affects the deeper layers of the skin and the subcutaneous tissues. It typically occurs when bacteria enter the skin through a break or crack, causing redness, swelling, and pain.</description></item><item><title>Cutaneous fungal infection</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Cutaneous-fungal-infection/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Cutaneous-fungal-infection/</guid><description>Dermatophytosis Dermatophytes digest keratin and so can cause infection of skin and keratiniszed structures - hair &amp;amp; nails. Tinea corporis, pedis, capitis, unguium</description></item><item><title>Folliculitis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Folliculitis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Folliculitis/</guid><description>Folliculitis is a common skin condition that causes red bumps or pustules around hair follicles. Infections (bacterial, fungal, or viral) and factors like friction, shaving, or a weakened immune system contribute to its development.</description></item><item><title>Headlice and Scabies</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Headlice-and-Scabies/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Headlice-and-Scabies/</guid><description>Head Lice Overview: Head lice are tiny insects that infest the hair and scalp, causing itching. Spread through head-to-head contact, especially common among children.</description></item><item><title>Impetigo</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Impetigo/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Impetigo/</guid><description>Impetigo is a highly contagious bacterial skin infection primarily affecting children, although it can occur in people of all ages. It is characterized by the development of red sores or blisters, often around the nose and mouth, which can burst and form golden-coloured crusts.</description></item><item><title>Lumps</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Lumps/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Lumps/</guid><description>Terminology Term Definition Abscess local accumulation of pus Bulla raised circumscribed lesion &amp;gt;5mm containing serous fluid (blister) above the dermis Comedone plug of dead epithelial material blocking pore: open (blackhead) or closed (whitehead) Erythema blanchable redness of the skin that can be localised or generalised (dilation of BVs and capillaries) Excoriation scratch which has broken the surface of skin Lichenification skin thickening with exaggerated skin markings as a result of repeated rubbing Macule flat well-defined area of altered skin pigmentation.</description></item><item><title>Melanoma</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Melanoma/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Melanoma/</guid><description>Melanoma is a type of skin cancer that originates from pigment-producing cells called melanocytes. It is known for its potential to metastasize (spread) to other parts of the body, making early detection and treatment crucial.</description></item><item><title>pyoderma gangrenosum</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/pyoderma-gangrenosum/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/pyoderma-gangrenosum/</guid><description>Pyoderma gangrenosum is a rare skin condition that causes painful ulcers. It&amp;rsquo;s usually treatable but can take some time to heal and may leave some scarring.</description></item><item><title>Sarcoidosis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Sarcoidosis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Sarcoidosis/</guid><description>Sarcoidosis is a rare inflammatory disease that can affect multiple organs, most commonly the lungs and lymph nodes. The condition is characterized by the formation of small clumps of inflammatory cells, known as granulomas, in various parts of the body.</description></item><item><title>Skin Ulcer</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Skin-Ulcers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Skin-Ulcers/</guid><description>Ulcer - loss of area of epidermis and dermis to produce a defect even down to fat, muscle, tendons and bone</description></item><item><title>Squamous cell carcinoma</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Squamous-cell-carcinoma/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Squamous-cell-carcinoma/</guid><description>May begin as [[Lumps#Solar (actinic) keratosis|solar (actinic) keratosis]] or be found on the lips of smokers or long standing ulcers (Marjolin&amp;rsquo;s ulcer)</description></item><item><title>Systemic Lupus Erythematosus</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Systemic-Lupus-Erythematosus/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Systemic-Lupus-Erythematosus/</guid><description>Systemic Lupus Erythematosus (SLE) is a complex autoimmune disease that can affect multiple organs and systems in the body. It is a Type III hypersensitivity reaction.</description></item><item><title>Urticaria</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Urticaria/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Urticaria/</guid><description>Urticaria, commonly known as hives, is a skin condition characterized by the sudden and transient appearance of red, raised, and intensely itchy welts or wheals on the skin.</description></item></channel></rss>