<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Respiratory on</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/tags/Respiratory/</link><description>Recent content in Respiratory on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://notes.nosos.co.uk/tags/Respiratory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Alpha-1-antitrypsin-deficiency/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Alpha-1-antitrypsin-deficiency/</guid><description>An inherited disorder affecting lung ([[emphysema]]) and liver ([[Liver Cirrhosis]]). A1AT is a glycoprotein and a serine protease inhibitor made in the liver which controls inflammatory cascades.</description></item><item><title>asthma</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/asthma/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/asthma/</guid><description>Characterised by episodes of dyspnoea, cough, wheeze Reversible airway obstruction and bronchospasm Inflammatory disorder reduces air flow rate Causes/Factors Exact cause of asthma still unknown but autoimmune/mast cell basophil degranulation</description></item><item><title>bronchiectasis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/bronchiectasis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/bronchiectasis/</guid><description>Chronic inflammation of bronchi and bronchioles leading to permanent dilation and thinning. Easily collapsible - obstructive lung disease
Causes/Factors Congenital: [[Cystic Fibrosis]], [[Young&amp;rsquo;s Syndrome]], [[Kartagener&amp;rsquo;s Syndrome]], [[Alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency]] Post-infection: measles, pertussis, [[pneumonia]], [[Tuberculosis]], [[HIV]] Other: Immunodeficiencies Symptoms Persistent productive cough (green/yellow colour) Dyspnoea Halitosis (bad breath) Repeated chest infections Signs Finger [[clubbing]] Coarse inspiratory crepitations heard Hypoxaemia Hypercapnia (high $CO_2$) Diagnostic Tests Sputum culture</description></item><item><title>bronchitis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/bronchitis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/bronchitis/</guid><description>Long-term inflammation of the bronchi.
To be classified as chronic bronchitis:
You must have a cough and mucus most days for at least 3 months a year, for 2 years in a row.</description></item><item><title>Chest X-Ray Interpretation</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Chest-X-Ray-Interpretation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Chest-X-Ray-Interpretation/</guid><description>[!info] Note for this page All of the images will have no pathology unless indicated otherwise
Quick check !</description></item><item><title>COPD</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/COPD/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/COPD/</guid><description>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease A common slowly progressive disorder characterised by airway obstruction Little to no reversibility (how to differentiate from [[asthma]]) Includes chronic [[bronchitis]] and [[emphysema]] Patients usually have either COPD or asthma not both Pink puffers and blue bloaters - likely ends of the spectrum:</description></item><item><title>cor pulmonale</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/cor-pulmonale/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/cor-pulmonale/</guid><description>Cor Pulmonale right sided [[Heart Failure]] caused by chronic pulmonary artery hypertension.
Causes/Factors [[COPD]] Pulmonary vascular disorders [[interstitial lung disease]] Thoracic cage abnormalities Sleep apnoea Symptoms Lack of perfusion</description></item><item><title>Cystic Fibrosis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Cystic-Fibrosis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Cystic-Fibrosis/</guid><description>1 in 25 people carry the mutation - autosomal recessive. Mutation in CFTR gene on chromosome 7
Causes/Factors Purely genetic condition, mutation leads to defect in chloride ion channel causing thickened mucus</description></item><item><title>emphysema</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/emphysema/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/emphysema/</guid><description>Defined histologically as enlarged air spaces distal to terminal bronchi with destruction of alveoli Over time, the inner walls of the air sacs weaken and rupture — creating larger air spaces instead of many small ones</description></item><item><title>Epiglottitis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Epiglottitis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Epiglottitis/</guid><description>Emergency cause of sore throat - life threatening. Notifiable disease
Causes/Factors H. influenzae type b the most common cause Other causes include strep pneumoniae and Group A Strep Symptoms Very acute onset Fever Stridor Signs Drooling Muffled voice Diagnostic Tests Do not examine the throat of anyone with suspected epiglottitis</description></item><item><title>Industrial dust diseases</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Industrial-dust-diseases/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Industrial-dust-diseases/</guid><description>For all of these diseases patients can claim compensation through Industrial Injuries Act
Coal worker&amp;rsquo;s pneumoconiosis A common dust disease in countries that have/had sub-terrain coal mines</description></item><item><title>Infectious Mononucleosis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Infectious-Mononucleosis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Infectious-Mononucleosis/</guid><description>Glandular fever Spread through saliva caused almost exclusively from EBV ![[z_attachments/Pasted image 20230823125619.png]]
Causes/Factors EBV virus colonisation, possibly at a older age than normal Symptoms Fatigue: Fever: Sore Throat: Swollen Lymph Nodes: Enlarged Spleen and Liver: Rash: Occasionally, a rash can develop.</description></item><item><title>Interstitial lung disease</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/interstitial-lung-disease/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/interstitial-lung-disease/</guid><description>Interstitial Lung Disease (ILD) refers to a group of lung disorders characterized by inflammation and scarring (fibrosis) of the lung parenchyma in a diffuse manner</description></item><item><title>Lung Abscess</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Lung-Abscess/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Lung-Abscess/</guid><description>A cavitating area of localised suppurative infection within the lung
Causes/Factors Inadequately treated [[pneumonia]] Aspiration Bronchial obstruction Pulmonary Infarction Subphrenic or hepatic abscess Clinical Features Swinging fever Productive cough - bad smelling sputum Pleuritic pain Haemoptysis Malaise Weight loss Finger [[clubbing]] Diagnostic Tests Bloods - FBC, ESR, CRP, culture Sputum culture CXR: walled cavity often with fluid level Bronchoscopy for specimen Management Antibiotics Drainage</description></item><item><title>Lung Tumours</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Lung-Tumours/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Lung-Tumours/</guid><description>Carcinoma of the bronchus - second most common cancer in UK, only 5% cured
Primary lung tumours 90% are carcinomas Non-small cell carcinoma 85% squamous cell carcinoma 20% - presence of keratinization adenocarcinoma 30% - mucin production large cell carcinoma 10% Small cell 15% - arise from endocrine cells -&amp;gt; excrete peptides -&amp;gt; paraneoplastic syndromes Main morphological difference between the two is nuclear characteristics and amount of cytoplasm.</description></item><item><title>Otitis Externa</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Otitis-Externa/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Otitis-Externa/</guid><description>Ear canal is the only skin-lined cul-de-sac in the body
Acute - Symptoms &amp;lt; 3/52 Typically unilateral 90&amp;amp; bacterial, 2% fungal Chronic - Symptoms &amp;gt; 3/52 Often bilateral White keratin debris may fill the ear over time Allergic dermatitis to shampoos/cosmetics etc Treat underlying cause Causes/Factors Swimming</description></item><item><title>Otitis media</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Otitis-media/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Otitis-media/</guid><description>Middle ear infection Fluid present in middle ear Very uncommon in children
Causes/Factors Viruses Similar bacteria as [[Otitis Externa]] Strep.</description></item><item><title>Pinna Cellulitis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Pinna-Cellulitis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Pinna-Cellulitis/</guid><description>Pinna Cellulitis is a bacterial skin infection affecting the external part of the ear, known as the pinna or auricle. Associated with trauma (ear piercing &amp;amp; acupuncture) surgery or burns</description></item><item><title>Pleural Effusion</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Pleural-Effusion/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Pleural-Effusion/</guid><description>Pleural effusion is a medical condition characterized by the accumulation of excess fluid in the pleural space. This buildup of fluid can compress the lungs, leading to breathing difficulties and other symptoms.</description></item><item><title>pneumonia</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/pneumonia/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/pneumonia/</guid><description>An acute lower respiratory tract infection associated with fever and other abnormal chest symptoms and signs
Causes/Factors Community acquired (CAP) - most common streptococcus pneumoniae.</description></item><item><title>pneumothorax</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/pneumothorax/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/pneumothorax/</guid><description>Air getting in pleural cavity causing collapse of the lung
Becomes a tensions pneumothorax when the pressure causes a shift in the mediastinum -&amp;gt; impairment of cardiopulmonary system</description></item><item><title>Pregnancy</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Pregnancy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Pregnancy/</guid><description>Pre-existing conditions and non-obstetric disease cause more maternal deaths in the UK than obstetric complications
Pregnant women should receive the same investigations and treatments as non-pregnant patients with avoidance of harm to the foetus wherever possible</description></item><item><title>pulmonary embolism</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/pulmonary-embolism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/pulmonary-embolism/</guid><description>Where a clot breaks off and gets lodged in lungs. Most commonly from a [[Deep Vein Thrombosis]]
Causes/Factors Same as [[Deep Vein Thrombosis]] Thrombophilia Symptoms Acute dyspnoea Pleuritic Haemoptysis Syncope Signs Pyrexia - usually low grade Cyanosis Tachycardia Tachypnoea Hypotension Raised JVP Diagnostic Tests Low $O_2$ Low $PaO_2$ elevated D-dimer (non specific) normal chest exam V/Q scan CTPA Management Oxygen Thrombolysis in life-threatening cases DOAC (-xban) LMWH in kidney failure patients</description></item><item><title>Pulmonary Fibrosis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Pulmonary-Fibrosis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Pulmonary-Fibrosis/</guid><description>Pulmonary fibrosis is a progressive lung disease characterized by the scarring and thickening of lung tissues. This scarring, known as fibrosis, makes it harder for the lungs to function properly and can result in breathing difficulties and reduced oxygen exchange.</description></item><item><title>Respiratory Exam</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Respiratory-Exam/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Respiratory-Exam/</guid><description>Introduction Wash hands (and don PPE if needed) Introduce yourself (name and role) Confirm patient&amp;rsquo;s name and DOB Explain what the examination involves Gain consent to continue Ask if patient in any pain before continuing General Inspection Clinical Signs Cyanosis Shortness of breath Cough - wet: [[pneumonia]], [[bronchiectasis]], [[COPD]], [[Cystic Fibrosis]] dry: [[asthma]], [[interstitial lung disease]] Wheeze/stridor Pallor Oedema Cachexia - malignancy and other end-stage respiratory diseases Objects and Equipment Oxygen delivery devices - type &amp;amp; rate Sputum pot Other medical equipment - oxygen, ECG, medications, catheters (note volume and colour), IV access Cigs or vapes Hands Inspection Colour: cyanosis of the hands may suggest underlying hypoxaemia.</description></item><item><title>Respiratory Failure</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Respiratory-Failure/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Respiratory-Failure/</guid><description>Type I hypoxia ($PaO_2 &amp;lt; 8kPa$) with a normal or low $PaCO_2$. Its caused primarily by V/Q mismatch, hypoventilation, abnormal diffusion, right to left cardiac shunts.</description></item><item><title>Sarcoidosis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Sarcoidosis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Sarcoidosis/</guid><description>Sarcoidosis is a rare inflammatory disease that can affect multiple organs, most commonly the lungs and lymph nodes. The condition is characterized by the formation of small clumps of inflammatory cells, known as granulomas, in various parts of the body.</description></item><item><title>Systemic Lupus Erythematosus</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Systemic-Lupus-Erythematosus/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Systemic-Lupus-Erythematosus/</guid><description>Systemic Lupus Erythematosus (SLE) is a complex autoimmune disease that can affect multiple organs and systems in the body. It is a Type III hypersensitivity reaction.</description></item><item><title>Tuberculosis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Tuberculosis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Tuberculosis/</guid><description>Mycobacterium tuberculosis - can affect almost any organ
Infects 1/3 of the world&amp;rsquo;s population - most common infectious cause of death</description></item></channel></rss>