<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Cardiovascular on</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/tags/Cardiovascular/</link><description>Recent content in Cardiovascular on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://notes.nosos.co.uk/tags/Cardiovascular/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Acute Coronary Syndrome</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Acute-Coronary-Syndrome/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Acute-Coronary-Syndrome/</guid><description>Acute coronary syndrome is a term used to describe a range of conditions associated with sudden, reduced blood flow to the heart.</description></item><item><title>Alcoholism</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Alcoholism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Alcoholism/</guid><description>An alcoholic is one whose problematic patter n of alcohol use leads to clinically significant impairment or distress, manifested by multiple psychosocial, behavioural or physiological features.</description></item><item><title>Angina</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Angina/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Angina/</guid><description>Pain due to partial blockage of a coronary vessel. Can be stable or unstable
stable angina (more common) – attacks have a trigger (such as stress or exercise) and stop within a few minutes of resting unstable angina (more serious) – attacks are more unpredictable (they may not have a trigger) and can continue despite resting Some people develop unstable angina after having stable angina.</description></item><item><title>Aortic Stenosis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Aortic-Stenosis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Aortic-Stenosis/</guid><description>Aortic stenosis - stiffening, narrowing
Pressure overload - high resistance low reps -&amp;gt; hypertrophy
Causes/Factors Congenital: bicuspid aortic value Calcification of the valve causing narrowing Age 65+ Symptoms [[Angina]] Breathlessness on exercise Pre-syncope/syncope Signs Hard and loud ejection systolic murmur Between S1 and S2 Reduced pulse pressure (difference between systolic and diastolic) Forceful apex beat Diagnostic Tests Echocardiogram - left hypertrophy with poor valve movement possible regurgitation ECG - poor R wave progression and stuff which I don&amp;rsquo;t understand yet Management If pressure difference between ventricle and aorta remains below 60 mmHg the patient is kept under observation</description></item><item><title>Atrial Fibrillation</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Atrial-Fibrillation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Atrial-Fibrillation/</guid><description>A rapid irregular atrial rhythm at 300-600 bpm. The AV node blocks most of these impulses and only responds intermittently (hence irregular QRS).</description></item><item><title>Cardiovascular examination</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Cardiovascular-examination/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Cardiovascular-examination/</guid><description>Introduction Wash hands (and don PPE if needed) Introduce yourself (name and role) Confirm patient&amp;rsquo;s name and DOB Explain what the examination involves Gain consent to continue Ask if patient in any pain before continuing General Inspection Clinical Signs Cyanosis Shortness of breath (congestive [[Heart Failure]], [[Pericarditis]] [[pneumonia]], [[pulmonary embolism]]) Pallor - not very sensitive - paleness -&amp;gt; anaemia (haemorrhage, chronic disease) or poor perfusion (congestive [[Heart Failure]]) Malar flush - plum red discolouration of the cheeks associated with [[Mitral stenosis]] Oedema - lots of causes, usually in limbs (pedal) or abdomen (ascites).</description></item><item><title>cerebral infarction</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/cerebral-infarction/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/cerebral-infarction/</guid><description>Two types - ischemia or haemorrhagic
Ischemic - clot blocks supply to distal parts of brain to where that clot got lodged Haemorrhagic - bleeding in the brain causing lack of perfusion (plus irritation to that part of brain)</description></item><item><title>Coronary Artery Disease</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Coronary-Artery-Disease/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Coronary-Artery-Disease/</guid><description>Coronary artery disease is a narrowing or blockage of your coronary arteries usually caused by the buildup of fatty material called plaque under the endothelium.</description></item><item><title>Deep Vein Thrombosis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Deep-Vein-Thrombosis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Deep-Vein-Thrombosis/</guid><description>Where a blood clot forms in a deep vein usually due to pooling of that blood due to lack of movement.</description></item><item><title>Fallot's Tetralogy</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Fallots-Tetralogy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Fallots-Tetralogy/</guid><description>Most common cyanotic congenital heart disorder + most common one that survives to adulthood
Tetralogy features:
Ventricular septal defect (VSD) [[Pulmonary stenosis]] Right ventricular hypertrophy Overriding aorta (aorta more central in heart and accepts right sided blood) Causes/Factors Congenital (both environmental and genetic factors) Severity of illness depends greatly on degree of pulmonary stenosis Symptoms With closure of ductus arteriosus infants become more cyanotic due to decreasing flow of blood to the lungs and increasing right to left flow across VSD Difficulty in feeding/gaining weight Delayed growth Dyspnoea of exertion Signs Children may squat during hypercyanotic spell as it increases systemic vascular resistance and temporary reversal of shunt Pulmonary murmur Diagnostic Tests Echo demonstrates abnormal anatomy ECG can also show hypertrophy Cardiac CT shows clearer anatomy valuable for surgery Management Oxygen Surgery to repair VSD and replace pulmonary valve Complications/red Flags pulmonary regurgitation RV outflow tract obstruction</description></item><item><title>Heart Block</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Heart-Block/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Heart-Block/</guid><description>Disrupted passage of electrical impulse through the AVN
1st-degree: prolonged PR interval, unchanging, no missed beats 2nd-degree (Mobitz I): PR interval becomes longer and longer until a QRS is missed.</description></item><item><title>Heart Failure</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Heart-Failure/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Heart-Failure/</guid><description>Defined as when cardiac output is inadequate for the body&amp;rsquo;s normal requirements. End stage of all cardiac pathologies
Systolic failure - inability of the ventricle to contract normally resulting in $\downarrow$ CO.</description></item><item><title>myocardial infarction</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/myocardial-infarction/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/myocardial-infarction/</guid><description>Belongs to a group of [[Acute Coronary Syndrome|acute coronary syndromes]] along with unstable [[Angina]]. These share a common pathology atherosclerotic plaque rupture, thrombosis and inflammation.</description></item><item><title>peripheral vascular disease</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/peripheral-vascular-disease/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/peripheral-vascular-disease/</guid><description>aka Peripheral arterial disease
Narrowing, blockage, or spasms in a blood vessel can cause PVD. PVD may affect any blood vessel outside of the heart including the arteries, veins, or lymphatic vessels.</description></item><item><title>Pregnancy</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Pregnancy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Pregnancy/</guid><description>Pre-existing conditions and non-obstetric disease cause more maternal deaths in the UK than obstetric complications
Pregnant women should receive the same investigations and treatments as non-pregnant patients with avoidance of harm to the foetus wherever possible</description></item><item><title>pulmonary embolism</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/pulmonary-embolism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/pulmonary-embolism/</guid><description>Where a clot breaks off and gets lodged in lungs. Most commonly from a [[Deep Vein Thrombosis]]
Causes/Factors Same as [[Deep Vein Thrombosis]] Thrombophilia Symptoms Acute dyspnoea Pleuritic Haemoptysis Syncope Signs Pyrexia - usually low grade Cyanosis Tachycardia Tachypnoea Hypotension Raised JVP Diagnostic Tests Low $O_2$ Low $PaO_2$ elevated D-dimer (non specific) normal chest exam V/Q scan CTPA Management Oxygen Thrombolysis in life-threatening cases DOAC (-xban) LMWH in kidney failure patients</description></item><item><title>Systemic Lupus Erythematosus</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Systemic-Lupus-Erythematosus/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Systemic-Lupus-Erythematosus/</guid><description>Systemic Lupus Erythematosus (SLE) is a complex autoimmune disease that can affect multiple organs and systems in the body. It is a Type III hypersensitivity reaction.</description></item><item><title>Tricuspid regurgitation</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Tricuspid-regurgitation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Tricuspid-regurgitation/</guid><description>Blood leaking back through the tricuspid valve
Causes/Factors Valve Abnormalities: Damage, degeneration, or enlargement of the tricuspid valve. Right Heart Enlargement: Enlargement of the right ventricle or right atrium can lead to TR.</description></item><item><title>Ventricular Fibrillation</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Ventricular-Fibrillation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Ventricular-Fibrillation/</guid><description>Disorganised chaotic electrical activity and contraction. The heart quivers (fibrillation) and CO falls to ~0
Causes/Factors Little warning of this condition before [[myocardial infarction]] [[Heart Failure]] Symptoms Possible</description></item></channel></rss>