<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Neurology on</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/tags/Neurology/</link><description>Recent content in Neurology on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://notes.nosos.co.uk/tags/Neurology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Alcoholism</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Alcoholism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Alcoholism/</guid><description>An alcoholic is one whose problematic patter n of alcohol use leads to clinically significant impairment or distress, manifested by multiple psychosocial, behavioural or physiological features.</description></item><item><title>Cognitive Assessment</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Cognitive-Assessment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Cognitive-Assessment/</guid><description>Introduction Wash hands (and don PPE if needed) Introduce yourself (name and role) Confirm patient&amp;rsquo;s name and DOB Explain what the examination involves Gain consent to continue Before starting, think about why you are assessing the patient’s cognitive function – what is your differential diagnosis from the history and mental state examination?</description></item><item><title>Delirium</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Delirium/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Delirium/</guid><description>Acute and fluctuating disturbance in attention and awareness
Need to differentiate from [[Dementias]]
Delirium Dementia Onset Acute Insidious Course Fluctuating Progressive Duration Days to weeks Months to years Consciousness Impaired Usually alert Attention Impaired Normal and then impaired Psychomotor changes Increased or decreased Often normal Hallucinations Common Less common (type dependant) Reversibility Usually reversible Progressive Collateral history may be very useful - if patient has capacity patient needs to consent for the collateral history to be taken.</description></item><item><title>Dementias</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Dementias/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Dementias/</guid><description>Type of Dementia Common Symptoms Pathology Risk Factors Treatment/Management Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease Amnesia, aphasia, agnosia, aprexia, associated behaviours (self neglect, personality changes, disinhibitions), steady decilne Amyloid plaques, neurofibrillary tangles in the brain Age, family history, genetics, certain genes, head injuries, cardiovascular disease, diabetes Medications (e.</description></item><item><title>Extradural haematoma</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Extradural-haematoma/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Extradural-haematoma/</guid><description>Beware deteriorating consciousness after any head injury that initially produced no LOC or after initial drowsiness seems to have resolved. This lucid interval pattern is typical of extradural bleeds</description></item><item><title>Horner's Syndrome</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Horners-Syndrome/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Horners-Syndrome/</guid><description>Also known as oculosympathetic palsy, is a neurological condition characterized by a set of symptoms resulting from disruption of the sympathetic nerve pathway that controls certain involuntary functions of the eye and face.</description></item><item><title>Intracranial venous thrombosis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Intracranial-venous-thrombosis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Intracranial-venous-thrombosis/</guid><description>Thrombosis of the cerebral sinuses or veins causes cerebral infarction but much rarer than arterial disease.
Seizures common and often focal.</description></item><item><title>Myotomes and Dermatomes</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Myotomes-and-Dermatomes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Myotomes-and-Dermatomes/</guid><description>The myotomes are the group of muscles innervated by a single spinal nerve root
Region Movement Level Region Movement Level Shoulder Abduction C5 Hip Flexion L1/2 Aduction C5-7 Adduction L2/3 Elbow Flexion C5/6 Extension L5/S1 Extension C7 Knee Flexion L5/S1 Wrist Flexion C7/8 Extension L3/4 Extension C7 Ankle Dorsiflexion L4 Fingers Flexion C8 Inversion L4 Extension C7 Eversion L5/S1 Abduction T1 Plantarflexion S1/2 Thumb abduction C8/T1 Toe Big toe extension L5 Dermatomes !</description></item><item><title>Neurogenic Bladder</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Neurogenic-Bladder/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Neurogenic-Bladder/</guid><description>Inability to properly empty the bladder due to neurological damage
Two types:
Spastic if an upper motor neurone damage Flaccid if damage to peripheral nerves (LMN) Causes/Factors UMN Stroke MS Spinal injury LMN Pregnancy Diabetes Alcohol (B12 deficiency) Symptoms Dysuria Frequency Urgency Abdominal distention Incontinence Diagnostic Tests Management Complications/red Flags Stasis -&amp;gt; UTI &amp;amp; urinary stones Inability to empty bladder -&amp;gt; hydroureter [[hydronephrosis]]</description></item><item><title>Parkinson's disease</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Parkinsons-disease/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Parkinsons-disease/</guid><description>Lack of dopamine Symptoms begin when 80% of dopamine producing cells (substantia nigra) have died Parkinsonism is anything that brings about these symptoms.</description></item><item><title>peripheral neuropathy</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/peripheral-neuropathy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/peripheral-neuropathy/</guid><description>Primary condition of the peripheral nerves causing symmetrical motor and/or sensory symptoms and signs in the limbs
Typically sensory change that is a symmetrical glove and stocking loss to all modalities.</description></item><item><title>Stroke</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Stroke/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Stroke/</guid><description>Two types - ischemia or haemorrhagic
Ischemic - clot blocks supply to distal parts of brain to where that clot got lodged !</description></item><item><title>Subarachnoid haemorrhage</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Subarachnoid-haemorrhage/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Subarachnoid-haemorrhage/</guid><description>Bleeding into the space between the arachnoid membrane and the pia mater - subarachnoid
Causes/Factors Aneurysms: Berry aneurysm rupture (80%) - common locations: junctions of posterior communicating with the internal carotid artery or anterior communicating with anterior cerebral artery Trauma: Head injury or trauma can lead to bleeding.</description></item><item><title>Subdural Haematoma</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Subdural-Haematoma/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Subdural-Haematoma/</guid><description>Very treatable condition in those whose conscious level fluctuates and in those having an &amp;ldquo;evolving stroke&amp;rdquo;
Bleeding is from bridging veins between the cortex and venous sinuses that are burst usually due to injury</description></item><item><title>Thoracic and Lumbar Spine Exam</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Thoracic-and-Lumbar-Spine-Exam/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Thoracic-and-Lumbar-Spine-Exam/</guid><description>Introduction Wash hands (and don PPE if needed) Introduce yourself (name and role) Confirm patient&amp;rsquo;s name and DOB Explain what the examination involves Gain consent to continue Ask if patient in any pain before continuing Look Observe the patient from behind to look for any scoliosis Then ask the patient to turn to the side to look for any exaggerated thoracic kyphosis or loss of normal lumbar lordosis.</description></item><item><title>Transient Ischemic Attack</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Transient-Ischemic-Attack/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Transient-Ischemic-Attack/</guid><description>Ischaemic usually embolic neurological event with symptoms that resolve within 24hr
Without intervention 1 in 12 patients subsequently have a stroke within a week</description></item><item><title>Vasovagal syncope</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Vasovagal-syncope/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Vasovagal-syncope/</guid><description>Vasovagal Syncope is a common cause of fainting (syncope) characterised by a sudden drop in heart rate and blood pressure, leading to a temporary loss of consciousness.</description></item></channel></rss>