<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>AIassisted on</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/tags/AIassisted/</link><description>Recent content in AIassisted on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://notes.nosos.co.uk/tags/AIassisted/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Angina</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Angina/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Angina/</guid><description>Pain due to partial blockage of a coronary vessel. Can be stable or unstable
stable angina (more common) – attacks have a trigger (such as stress or exercise) and stop within a few minutes of resting unstable angina (more serious) – attacks are more unpredictable (they may not have a trigger) and can continue despite resting Some people develop unstable angina after having stable angina.</description></item><item><title>Benign Prostatic Hyperplasia</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Benign-Prostatic-Hyperplasia/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Benign-Prostatic-Hyperplasia/</guid><description>Benign Prostatic Hyperplasia (BPH) is a non-cancerous enlargement of the prostate gland, which is located just below the bladder and surrounds the urethra.</description></item><item><title>Cryptorchidism</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Cryptorchidism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Cryptorchidism/</guid><description>Cryptorchidism, also known as undescended testis, is a condition in which one or both testicles do not descend into the scrotum during fetal development.</description></item><item><title>Glomerulonephritis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Glomerulonephritis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Glomerulonephritis/</guid><description>Glomerulonephritis, often referred to as GN, is a group of kidney diseases that involve inflammation of the glomeruli—the tiny filtering units in the kidneys responsible for removing waste and excess fluid from the blood.</description></item><item><title>Grave's disease</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Graves-disease/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Graves-disease/</guid><description>Brief Overview Grave&amp;rsquo;s disease is an autoimmune disorder and the most common cause of [[hyperthyroidism]]. In this condition, the body&amp;rsquo;s immune system mistakenly attacks the thyroid gland, leading to an excessive production of thyroid hormones.</description></item><item><title>Horner's Syndrome</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Horners-Syndrome/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Horners-Syndrome/</guid><description>Also known as oculosympathetic palsy, is a neurological condition characterized by a set of symptoms resulting from disruption of the sympathetic nerve pathway that controls certain involuntary functions of the eye and face.</description></item><item><title>Hyperthyroidism</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Hyperthyroidism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Hyperthyroidism/</guid><description>Brief Overview Hyperthyroidism is a medical condition characterized by excessive production of thyroid hormones by the thyroid gland. Thyroid hormones, primarily thyroxine (T4) and triiodothyronine (T3), play a crucial role in regulating the body&amp;rsquo;s metabolism.</description></item><item><title>Infectious Mononucleosis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Infectious-Mononucleosis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Infectious-Mononucleosis/</guid><description>Glandular fever Spread through saliva caused almost exclusively from EBV ![[z_attachments/Pasted image 20230823125619.png]]
Causes/Factors EBV virus colonisation, possibly at a older age than normal Symptoms Fatigue: Fever: Sore Throat: Swollen Lymph Nodes: Enlarged Spleen and Liver: Rash: Occasionally, a rash can develop.</description></item><item><title>Minimal change disease</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Minimal-change-disease/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Minimal-change-disease/</guid><description>Minimal Change Disease (MCD) is a type of kidney disorder characterised by damage to the glomeruli. No change on histology under light microscopy</description></item><item><title>Nephritic syndrome</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Nephritic-syndrome/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Nephritic-syndrome/</guid><description>Difference between nephritic and [[Nephrotic syndrome|nephrotic]] syndrome
haematuria in nephritic proteinuria in [[Nephrotic syndrome|nephrotic]] Causes/Factors Infections: Certain bacterial infections, such as streptococcal infections, can trigger immune responses that affect the glomeruli.</description></item><item><title>Pleural Effusion</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Pleural-Effusion/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Pleural-Effusion/</guid><description>Pleural effusion is a medical condition characterized by the accumulation of excess fluid in the pleural space. This buildup of fluid can compress the lungs, leading to breathing difficulties and other symptoms.</description></item><item><title>Polycystic Kidney Disease</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Polycystic-Kidney-Disease/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Polycystic-Kidney-Disease/</guid><description>Polycystic kidney disease is an inherited condition that causes small fluid-filled sacs called cysts to develop in the kidneys.
Autosomal Dominant (ADPKD) PKD1/2 mutation Small change - present as adults Rarely any symptoms with child with the condition.</description></item><item><title>Prostatic Adenocarcinoma</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Prostatic-Adenocarcinoma/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Prostatic-Adenocarcinoma/</guid><description>Cancer of the glandular epithelium in the prostate
Causes/Factors Male% Ethnicity FH - BRCA1/2 Pesticide exposure Risk of cancer $\approx$ age</description></item><item><title>Pulmonary Fibrosis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Pulmonary-Fibrosis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Pulmonary-Fibrosis/</guid><description>Pulmonary fibrosis is a progressive lung disease characterized by the scarring and thickening of lung tissues. This scarring, known as fibrosis, makes it harder for the lungs to function properly and can result in breathing difficulties and reduced oxygen exchange.</description></item><item><title>pyoderma gangrenosum</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/pyoderma-gangrenosum/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/pyoderma-gangrenosum/</guid><description>Pyoderma gangrenosum is a rare skin condition that causes painful ulcers. It&amp;rsquo;s usually treatable but can take some time to heal and may leave some scarring.</description></item><item><title>Sarcoidosis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Sarcoidosis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Sarcoidosis/</guid><description>Sarcoidosis is a rare inflammatory disease that can affect multiple organs, most commonly the lungs and lymph nodes. The condition is characterized by the formation of small clumps of inflammatory cells, known as granulomas, in various parts of the body.</description></item></channel></rss>