<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Rheumatology on</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/tags/Rheumatology/</link><description>Recent content in Rheumatology on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://notes.nosos.co.uk/tags/Rheumatology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Crystal Arthritis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Crystal-Arthritis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Crystal-Arthritis/</guid><description>aka Gout
Causes/Factors Too much uric acid in blood - kidneys not excreting properly, crystallises out in joints Symptoms Severe pain - can&amp;rsquo;t bare weight Feet and knee are classic locations Diuretics Give good analgesics Signs Diagnostic Tests White toothpaste like fluid removed from the joint with syringe Management Some drug which fixes it in a few months/years</description></item><item><title>Inflammatory Arthritis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Inflammatory-Arthritis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Inflammatory-Arthritis/</guid><description>Usually the lining of the joint that gets affected Anyone at any age can get inflammatory arthritis
Rheumatoid Arthritis ^ab6a7d</description></item><item><title>Osteoarthritis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Osteoarthritis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Osteoarthritis/</guid><description>&amp;ldquo;Wear and tear&amp;rdquo; - nothing to do from immune system
Cartilage flakes off Fragments of cartilage triggers slight inflammatory reaction Bone form cysts as tries to remodel Causes/Factors Age Occupation Athlete (doing something to accelerate wear) Symptoms Inflammation around the joint (in bone and joint) Pain around the joint Weaker muscles (due to lack of use due to pain) Diagnostic Tests Clinical examination XR findings Normal CRP and antibodies Does not affect other organs Management Complications/red Flags</description></item><item><title>Sarcoidosis</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Sarcoidosis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Sarcoidosis/</guid><description>Sarcoidosis is a rare inflammatory disease that can affect multiple organs, most commonly the lungs and lymph nodes. The condition is characterized by the formation of small clumps of inflammatory cells, known as granulomas, in various parts of the body.</description></item><item><title>Sjögren's syndrome</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Sj%C3%B6grens-syndrome/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Sj%C3%B6grens-syndrome/</guid><description>Sjögren&amp;rsquo;s Syndrome is a chronic autoimmune disorder characterized by inflammation and dysfunction of the exocrine glands, primarily the salivary and lacrimal glands.</description></item><item><title>Systemic Lupus Erythematosus</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Systemic-Lupus-Erythematosus/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Systemic-Lupus-Erythematosus/</guid><description>Systemic Lupus Erythematosus (SLE) is a complex autoimmune disease that can affect multiple organs and systems in the body. It is a Type III hypersensitivity reaction.</description></item></channel></rss>