<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>OSCE on</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/tags/OSCE/</link><description>Recent content in OSCE on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://notes.nosos.co.uk/tags/OSCE/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Abdominal Exam</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Abdominal-Exam/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Abdominal-Exam/</guid><description>Introduction Wash hands (and don PPE if needed) Introduce yourself (name and role) Confirm patient&amp;rsquo;s name and DOB Explain what the examination involves Gain consent to continue Ask if patient in any pain before continuing General Inspection Clinical Signs Body habitus - slim, obese, cachexic Scars Jaundice Abdominal distension Masses Pallor Objects and Equipment Stoma bags - location and type Vomit bowl Surgical drains - note location and type/volume of contents Feeding tubes NG or NJ Medical equipment - oxygen, ECG, medications, catheters (note volume and colour), IV access Mobility aids Vital sign charts Fluid balance charts Prescriptions Hands Inspection [[Koilonychia]] - iron-deficiency anaemia (malabsorption, Crohn&amp;rsquo;s) &amp;amp; [[leukonychia]] - hypoalbuminaemia (5+) Palmar erythema (redness) -chronic liver disease, [[Pregnancy]] Dupuytren&amp;rsquo;s contracture - thickening of palmar fascia $\rightarrow$ alcoholic liver disease Finger [[Clubbing]] Most likely causes to come up in abdo exam OSCE is [[inflammatory bowel disease]], [[Coeliac Disease]], [[Liver Cirrhosis]] and lymphoma of GI tract</description></item><item><title>Basic Clinical Skills</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Basic-Clinical-Skills/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Basic-Clinical-Skills/</guid><description>Vital signs Temperature, pulse, respiratory rate, blood pressure and SpO2.
Gather equipment Ear thermometer Disposable tip Oxygen sats probe Sphygmomanometer Stethoscope - cleaned with alcohol wipes For each explain the procedure and wash hands</description></item><item><title>Blood Test Interpretation</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Blood-Test-Interpretation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Blood-Test-Interpretation/</guid><description>Full Blood Count Component What the Test Shows High Levels (Possible Causes) Low Levels (Possible Causes) Hemoglobin (Hb) Oxygen-carrying capacity of red blood cells.</description></item><item><title>Breast Exam</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Breast-Exam/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Breast-Exam/</guid><description>Introduction Wash hands (and don PPE if needed) Introduce yourself (name and role) Confirm patient&amp;rsquo;s name and DOB Explain what the examination involves - using patient friendly language Explain the need for a chaperone “One of the female ward staff members will be present throughout the examination, acting as a chaperone, would that be ok?</description></item><item><title>Cardiovascular examination</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Cardiovascular-examination/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Cardiovascular-examination/</guid><description>Introduction Wash hands (and don PPE if needed) Introduce yourself (name and role) Confirm patient&amp;rsquo;s name and DOB Explain what the examination involves Gain consent to continue Ask if patient in any pain before continuing General Inspection Clinical Signs Cyanosis Shortness of breath (congestive [[Heart Failure]], [[Pericarditis]] [[pneumonia]], [[pulmonary embolism]]) Pallor - not very sensitive - paleness -&amp;gt; anaemia (haemorrhage, chronic disease) or poor perfusion (congestive [[Heart Failure]]) Malar flush - plum red discolouration of the cheeks associated with [[Mitral stenosis]] Oedema - lots of causes, usually in limbs (pedal) or abdomen (ascites).</description></item><item><title>Chest X-Ray Interpretation</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Chest-X-Ray-Interpretation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Chest-X-Ray-Interpretation/</guid><description>[!info] Note for this page All of the images will have no pathology unless indicated otherwise
Quick check !</description></item><item><title>Cognitive Assessment</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Cognitive-Assessment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Cognitive-Assessment/</guid><description>Introduction Wash hands (and don PPE if needed) Introduce yourself (name and role) Confirm patient&amp;rsquo;s name and DOB Explain what the examination involves Gain consent to continue Before starting, think about why you are assessing the patient’s cognitive function – what is your differential diagnosis from the history and mental state examination?</description></item><item><title>Cranial Nerve Exam</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Cranial-Nerve-Exam/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Cranial-Nerve-Exam/</guid><description>Introduction Wash hands (and don PPE if needed) Introduce yourself (name and role) Confirm patient&amp;rsquo;s name and DOB Explain what the examination involves Gain consent to continue Ask if patient in any pain before continuing General Observation Conscious level</description></item><item><title>Falls History Taking</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Falls-History-Taking/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Falls-History-Taking/</guid><description>Introduction Wash hands (and don PPE if needed) Introduce yourself (name and role) Confirm patient&amp;rsquo;s name and DOB Explain that you&amp;rsquo;d like to take a history from them Gain consent to continue Ask if patient in any pain before continuing Presenting complaint Start with open questions: &amp;ldquo;How can I help today?</description></item><item><title>GALS Exam</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/GALS-Exam/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/GALS-Exam/</guid><description>Introduction Wash hands (and don PPE if needed)
Introduce yourself (name and role)
Confirm patient&amp;rsquo;s name and DOB</description></item><item><title>Glasgow Coma Scale</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Glasgow-Coma-Scale/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Glasgow-Coma-Scale/</guid><description>The Glasgow Coma Scale (GCS) is a neurological assessment tool used to evaluate a patient&amp;rsquo;s level of consciousness and neurological functioning.</description></item><item><title>History Taking</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/History-Taking/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/History-Taking/</guid><description>Introduction Wash hands (and don PPE if needed) Introduce yourself (name and role) Confirm patient&amp;rsquo;s name and DOB Explain what history you&amp;rsquo;d like to take Gain consent to continue Presenting complaint Start with open questions: &amp;ldquo;How can I help today?</description></item><item><title>Knee MSK Exam</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Knee-Joint-Exam/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Knee-Joint-Exam/</guid><description>Introduction Wash hands (and don PPE if needed) Introduce yourself (name and role) Confirm patient&amp;rsquo;s name and DOB Explain what the examination involves Gain consent to continue Ask if patient in any pain before continuing Look Ask the patient to expose their legs before beginning the exam Look for any redness, swelling, inflammation etc Look for any signs of muscle wastage - particularly in the quadriceps Scars or deformities Any walking aids - how did they walk into the consultation?</description></item><item><title>Lower Limb Vascular Exam</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Lower-Limb-Vascular-Exam/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Lower-Limb-Vascular-Exam/</guid><description>Introduction Wash hands (and don PPE if needed) Introduce yourself (name and role) Confirm patient&amp;rsquo;s name and DOB Explain what the examination involves Gain consent to continue Ask if patient in any pain before continuing Gather equipment General Inspection Clinical Signs General appearance and alertness Obvious limb amputation Objects and Equipment Medical equipment - oxygen, ECG, medications, catheters (note volume and colour), IV access Mobility aids Prosthetic limbs Vital sign charts Fluid balance charts Prescription Inspection of legs, foot and toes Colour Oedema Ulceration, trauma, which the patient might not be complaining about due to [[Diabetes Mellitus]] neuropathy Varicose veins Missing digits Check in-between toes and back of legs for fungal infections/ulcers trophic skins changes: hair loss, discoloured skin, dry skin, thickened nails 6 Ps of acute limb ischaemia Pale Pulseless Painful Paralysed Paraesthetic Perishingly cold Palpation &amp;amp; Auscultation Capillary Refill time Apply 5 seconds of pressure onto finger and release Should return in &amp;lt;2 seconds If &amp;gt;2 seconds suggests poor peripheral perfusion (hypovolaemia, congestive heart failure) and need to assess central cap refill Gross motor Ask the patient to wiggle their toes Assess temperature and sensation Using back of hand, start at toes and compare each side Ask the patient to close their eyes and use light touch to assess for any sensory deficit Check oedema Is it pitting or firm Palpate arteries Compare side to side</description></item><item><title>Mental State Exam</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Mental-State-Exam/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Mental-State-Exam/</guid><description>Appearance Observe the patient’s general appearance:
Personal hygiene: are there any signs of self-neglect? Clothing: are they dressed appropriately for the weather/circumstances?</description></item><item><title>Myotomes and Dermatomes</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Myotomes-and-Dermatomes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Myotomes-and-Dermatomes/</guid><description>The myotomes are the group of muscles innervated by a single spinal nerve root
Region Movement Level Region Movement Level Shoulder Abduction C5 Hip Flexion L1/2 Aduction C5-7 Adduction L2/3 Elbow Flexion C5/6 Extension L5/S1 Extension C7 Knee Flexion L5/S1 Wrist Flexion C7/8 Extension L3/4 Extension C7 Ankle Dorsiflexion L4 Fingers Flexion C8 Inversion L4 Extension C7 Eversion L5/S1 Abduction T1 Plantarflexion S1/2 Thumb abduction C8/T1 Toe Big toe extension L5 Dermatomes !</description></item><item><title>Psychiatric History Taking</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Psychiatric-History-Taking/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Psychiatric-History-Taking/</guid><description>Table to fill out in your mind for a psychological condition.
Biological Phsychological Social Predisposing Precipitating Perpetuating Protective Introduction Wash hands (and don PPE if needed) Introduce yourself (name and role) Confirm patient&amp;rsquo;s name and DOB Establish rapport with the patient early on - explain that some of the questions may be difficult to answer Reassure that everything will be kept confidential (unless there is a risk to them or another person) Make sure to signpost that you will be covering many areas - may need to interrupt if you already have enough information to keep to time Presenting complaint Use open questions and provide the patient enough time to answer</description></item><item><title>Respiratory Exam</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Respiratory-Exam/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Respiratory-Exam/</guid><description>Introduction Wash hands (and don PPE if needed) Introduce yourself (name and role) Confirm patient&amp;rsquo;s name and DOB Explain what the examination involves Gain consent to continue Ask if patient in any pain before continuing General Inspection Clinical Signs Cyanosis Shortness of breath Cough - wet: [[pneumonia]], [[bronchiectasis]], [[COPD]], [[Cystic Fibrosis]] dry: [[asthma]], [[interstitial lung disease]] Wheeze/stridor Pallor Oedema Cachexia - malignancy and other end-stage respiratory diseases Objects and Equipment Oxygen delivery devices - type &amp;amp; rate Sputum pot Other medical equipment - oxygen, ECG, medications, catheters (note volume and colour), IV access Cigs or vapes Hands Inspection Colour: cyanosis of the hands may suggest underlying hypoxaemia.</description></item><item><title>Sick Day Rules</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Sick-Day-Rules/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Sick-Day-Rules/</guid><description>Some medications require good kidney function. During sick days or periods of dehydration they should be stopped to preserve the kidneys.</description></item><item><title>Thoracic and Lumbar Spine Exam</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Thoracic-and-Lumbar-Spine-Exam/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Thoracic-and-Lumbar-Spine-Exam/</guid><description>Introduction Wash hands (and don PPE if needed) Introduce yourself (name and role) Confirm patient&amp;rsquo;s name and DOB Explain what the examination involves Gain consent to continue Ask if patient in any pain before continuing Look Observe the patient from behind to look for any scoliosis Then ask the patient to turn to the side to look for any exaggerated thoracic kyphosis or loss of normal lumbar lordosis.</description></item><item><title>Thyroid Exam</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Thyroid-Exam/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Thyroid-Exam/</guid><description>Gather equipment Stethoscope Glass of water Tendon hammer Piece of paper Introduction Wash hands (and don PPE if needed) Introduce yourself (name and role) Confirm patient&amp;rsquo;s name and DOB Explain what the examination involves Gain consent to continue Ask if patient in any pain before continuing General Inspection Clinical Signs Weight - weight loss a/w [[Hyperthyroidism]], weight gain a/w [[Hypothyroidism]] Behaviour - anxiety and hyperactivity with [[Hyperthyroidism]], low mood with [[Hypothyroidism]] Clothing - may be inappropriate for the current temperature Hoarse voice - caused by compression of the larnx due to enlargement [[Hypothyroidism]] Slurred and slow voice - [[Hyperthyroidism]] Objects and Equipment Mobility aids - patients with [[Hyperthyroidism]] can develop proximal myopathy Prescriptions - eg levothyroxine Hands Inspection Thyroid acropachy - similar appearance to clubbing caused by phalangeal bone overgrowth secondary to [[Grave&amp;rsquo;s disease]] Onycholysis - detachment of nail from the bed a/w [[Hyperthyroidism]] -Palmar erythema - reddening of palms a/w [[Hyperthyroidism]] Peripheral tremor A feature of hyperthyroidism due to sympathetic nervous system overactivity</description></item><item><title>Upper and Lower Limb Neurological Exam</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Upper-and-Lower-Limb-Neurological-Exam/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Upper-and-Lower-Limb-Neurological-Exam/</guid><description>Quick reference Neuro exams always try to localise where in the pathway the lesion is: upper (brain, spinal cord) or lower (nerve root, peripheral nerve, NMJ or muscle).</description></item><item><title>Venepuncture</title><link>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Venepuncture/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://notes.nosos.co.uk/Venepuncture/</guid><description>Prepare equipment Kidney dish Vacuum sample bottles Gauze swab Non-sterile gloves ChloraPrep/alcohol wipe Plaster Sharps bin Vacutainer Tourniquet Blood request form + stickers!</description></item></channel></rss>